man and there's John hi John how are you
we are well let's see to what do I want
I want you know there we go okay you
know welcome we were just chatting a bit
that's good so what do we yeah tell me
about yourself John I just know the
little bit that I that I saw online I
saw that you wrote a book on zombies and
that the students loved you for which
both both of which I commend you so I
think how Jared came in contact with me
was for the video series I've done -
okay
awakening from the meeting process how I
came to that is I am an associate
professor of cognitive psychology and
cognitive science at the University of
Toronto okay I'm also a long-term
practitioner and teacher of the past 'no
matter Tai Chi Chuan related practices
so I study a lot about the the nature of
the intelligence in sight mindfulness
wisdom meaning in life and then that
connects up to that I'm also in the
cognitive science program I'm yeah I
think I'm the teacher that's been had
the longest history at the University of
Toronto in cognitive science right now
and and the work I do there has to do
with connecting those things I just
spoke to you about especially meaning
and intelligence to a lot of the
emerging work coming out of machine
learning and artificial intelligence I
think I call relevance realization and
then how we can use that to understand
that sense a deep connection and coupled
being coupled to ourselves each other in
the world that I think is actually
the core process were metaphorically
referring to when we use this notion of
meaning in life we're trying to point to
that that sense of connectedness and I
think the the emerging empirical
research shows that that's ultimately is
these factors of connectedness that
really contribute to people's sense of
meaning in life but I think you can also
understand those in terms of really
essential processes for our cognitive
agency of fitting us to the world in an
appropriate and deep way for affording
our cognitive agency and the development
of it yeah and so that then leads me
into stuff where I overlap with your
work you know at which I'm you do this
the way in which people deeply I don't
have you've seen any of the talks have
given on this but the way people deeply
use symbols I don't use symbols in an
ornamental cents a unit I use it in a
sense that I think is very resonant with
urban sensitive the imaginal as I
understand it wrong and that that that
that that people are making use of
symbols to activate and access this
profound connectedness that has a
phenomenological experiential aspect to
it but also a functional aspect to it
that I call religio and again I see that
resonant with a lot of what I'm reading
in Corbin and in your work and I think
that's all important to the central
project of awakening from the meaning
crisis because I see Corbin along with
people like Heidegger of course had a
huge influence on Corbin young Barfield
and Tillich as sort of record of this
the crisis of meaning that we've entered
into and I'm interested in talking to
you because if that in in I have it
I think it's episodes 47 and 48 or 48
and 49 I talk about German yeah yeah
and so yeah I haven't got
so busy I haven't gotten around to it
yet but they're all busy yeah that's
from trying fam and I get that yeah I'm
just trying to answer your question of
how it who I am and how it is I can yeah
you could contact with your work you
should know I do recommend your work
quite highly thanks I get in contact
with people precisely because they seem
you talk about you on the videos okay
sweet that's great I did I'm delighted
any yeah that's that's that's that's
cool Wow
I you cover a lot of bases that's that's
pretty
I mean it's you're in an odd position
being in cognitive science yeah
psychology but I had also have explicit
educational training in philosophy of
yes well yeah and so and then and then
the part of philosophy that is most
connective between the philosophy and
the work they do in cognitive psychology
and even in cognitive sciences ancient
philosophy so of a deep education and
sort of Plato photonic schools appear
like this stoicism so you can also see
there while I'm resonating with Corbin
so deeply yeah yeah so so I mean where
would that the the diamond I met in kind
of an odd place right now because I
think I'm because I think I'm actually
starting to be able to walk the talk as
it were
yeah yeah I'm so so I'm teaching the I'm
teaching online to a small group of
people who you know follow me around
yeah it's and and so what I struggle
with is the same sort of thing that I'm
looking for really good ways to to wake
people up boy it's right it's a you know
it's kind it's kind
hard to talk about this stuff without
without using language that has the
wrong connotations or at least that
seemed wrong to me but I but there's got
to be better ways than I have yet
managed to develop to to bring people
around to something which is it's not
really very intellectual it can be you
know but that if you're if you're a head
person like me that that provides more
that that's more trouble than it's worth
in a lot of ways you can't you can't
think your way into into meaning I mean
actually you kind of can but well that's
actually interesting because that's one
of the key arguments I consider in the
couple episodes where I talk about
Korbin and I make worker some Miki
system work by la Paul and Agnes Collard
la Paul's book on transformative
experience and Callard excellent book on
aspiration about and they basically have
arguments that this kind of move you
know if some kind of self transcendence
for lack of a better term if you want to
pay waking up that's fine waking up
experience though I'm not really gonna
slow us down with the metaphors of what
I'm saying rest standing or some
development of gains here right and that
the argument that they both make when
they talk about transformative
experience in its aspiration is it's not
something you can infer your way through
they actually have some deep arguments
as to why you can't infer your way
through it but they all but alert in
particular makes a very good point about
this she says look if this process is
not he's not ultimately inferential in
nature and we conclude that because it's
not infrared and so it's off also not
rational then we're gonna get into a
weird place because she's she rightly
points out the aspiration to rationality
is a clear case
aspiration and if we said well
aspiration is not a rational process
because it's not an inferential process
then we get into a weird performative
contradiction which is a really kind of
cool move this actually leads me to my
peers that are really interesting to me
in Corbin
which is the idea that well how do we do
it then how do and then there and this
is where I think you know the symbolic
relationship to the future self is not
an imaginary relationship but an
imaginal one in some important way I'm
really interested in because kowler
talks about you get into this weird
paradox your current self is causing
that future self but the future self has
the normative authority in the ultimate
justification for the whole project and
so you get into this and I actually like
picked up like right on that sort of
niche here in the in the chapter on the
visionary recital page 81 there's
there's this quote this very aspiration
this longing and nostalgia of constitute
and bring into being an intermediary
universe a world of archetypal personal
figures the world of the imagination I
thought that was amazing that's exactly
what I'm seeing oh I forget how do I
pronounce your last name chief um yeah I
mean if it were if we wrote England it
would be Cheatham but we've always used
chief absurd go with either one well I'm
an emblem it's children mispronouncing
it's all corrected from there on in so
please forgive me if you're well here's
the more the more difficult one is your
last name Verve a key
okay got it
so points though to a quote and there's
other passages like that in your books
where I see this
language coming out of like out of like
break the core of analytic philosophy in
one hand and yet you are talking in a
way that's deeply resonant with it and I
see Corbin as like affording that kind
of connection which is very interesting
to me well for yeah well we did yeah
this is always yeah I'm I'm kind of in
this and when I'm writing two or three
essays right now and then I'm teaching
and so hi so I'm in this but I'm in a
place that is partly pertinent and
partly not but it is pertinent because
look for Corbin I think it's fair to say
that that and any kind of I want to say
this the the archetypal example of
knowledge is interpersonal dialogue you
know that one of the central places in
all of one of the central moments in all
of his work is in creative imagination
where he talks about the prayer of man
and the prayer of God and says that
prayer is the supreme form and the
highest act of creative imagination and
and the first time you'd come to that he
used his language in such a way that it
seems obvious that he's talking about
making up your own God and yet you know
that he doesn't mean that and and and
and and so so that's the that's the the
archetype of of knowledge for him it's
always personal and somebody see one of
the students said the other day well as
the is the angel you or is it not you
and I I wish I knew I wish I knew a
little more about contemporary you know
woven us and and people like that
because I think what Corbin is
suggesting is has a lot of resonance
with with Lebanon you know you you are
the other and the other is you and you
can't possibly social
there's there's this but the other isn't
just other people it's also other
aspects of you of you right in time oh
yeah you're indelibly a historical as
well oh well for court for Corbin
history yeah
Corbin's about you know escaping the
bonds of history but I don't think
Gordon wants to deny that you're that
he's not trying to deny the high
daguerreian idea that we're all so right
no but what's important for him wait
wait where where does the forecourt by
the the the I'd almost had a good word
for this that the substance of things
the volume of things the space of things
the imagination of things the resonance
of things the soul of things none of
that comes from history I mean he's
trying to break out of sort of the
narrative of horizontal history yeah
right yeah and so they're sort of
metaphors I get it that you know the the
ontological is sort of vertical for him
what I meant was though that like I'm
just trying to bring let's go back to
the way I phrased it is the other not
only other people but I'm there's a
sense of which there's other to myself
that's what I was trying to point to
when I invoked history of history is the
wrong word off I'll take it back because
yeah because that dr.ali tends to get
misread yeah that's fine and so again
obviously in Lebanon you see it in use
and the objective you know the triple L
ontologies of like that okay well you
see the point is they say that's the
case for every object that we encounter
every object right is both shining
towards us in a way but always
withdrawing okay
in a profound way so we're always
encounter and I was using this when I
was doing to talk about trying to say
there's a sense because I think it's
clear in Corbin but that that really
that at divine double while I use stangs
what we'll come back to in a second on
double right isn't just with other
persons it's with other aspects of
ourselves and even even with what we
typically call odd no absolutely no no
no no precise ly that that that
archetype is stands for every kind of
relationship that you're that's what
that's what that that's why it's
perfectly legitimate I think to call
Corbin an animist everything is animated
I mean he he you know he's he's flying
off the Zoroastrians so he's a little
careful about what he says but he at
least says that every beam of light has
an angel I'm perfectly happy to say that
every being has an angel he's got to say
well you know it's only the beings of
light there's some beings of darkness
but we don't need to talk about those so
so that the so that you're always in an
intimate quasi personal relationship
with every object otherwise there is no
experience at all you know I mean I
think I think that's I think that's what
not just me making up what Corbin is
saying I think that's what he's saying
he says what would a world without a
look without a face actually be it would
be nothing so so so that every
relationship you know denigrate it by
calling it personification and you know
this this pencil isn't very much like a
person but in order to engage with it in
any way at all you have to personify it
it's kind of like a penis it's kind of
like a rocket the human puts it this way
that the anima Mundi is the availability
of
world to the imagination and that sort
of puts it on the psychological side and
Corbin says well yeah sure that's right
but that's because because everything
has an angel so so so did this yeah
there are no objects there's a you know
he says and right right at the beginning
he says there are no objects
everything's a person and he gets that
from Zoroaster history at least he
claims to you know you might be
interested in some work I'm doing
currently where you show where you see
this coming out and people who are
literally rocket scientists so these are
people who bring the Rovers around on
Mars right and in order to move the
Rovers around they're looking for people
getting the ability to be on Mars yeah
so and that's really difficult because
because of the time lag there's no
control right so they have to rely on
their imagination naj him away and so
what they do is they and vertice in her
book on seemed like the rover they both
she uses his meat they cantaloupe they
both personify the rover but they also
techno morph eyes themselves bazzill and
they'll say I I need to do this and they
practice to get this loop going
they couple themselves in an imaginal
sense and over and that kind of I call
that participatory knowing that project
that's right yeah it's like to be on
Mars and I and only then can they do
this
do the skills and then only after doing
the skills do they get to the level of
the propositions of the beliefs it's
fantastic but it's perfect that's that's
really great yeah that's fantastic not
just being you
they'll say things like you know I was
gardening and my right hand kept getting
stuck in the garden and then when I went
to the lab the Rovers right wheel was
stuck and they sort of like I'm
interested in what's going on they're
cognitively obviously but I want to
connect that by things like Corvin
participatory knowing the imaginal -
right okay these issues about meaning
because notice what's happening here
they're they're getting a sense of
extended identity it's obviously not a
logical extension of identity and
they're doing this thing we're just
talking about the other nests of the
rover is somehow being they're entering
into this coupling with it really it
becomes deeply meaningful to them they
they get they get deeply you know beyond
utilitarian money and time
oh hell oh yeah now they get deeply
worried that's fantastic yeah that's
yeah that's a really good story I'll try
to use it in class science conference at
the University of Toronto I'm going to
be mocking buddy and how it exemplifies
all the kinds of knowing that are
underneath the propositional knowing and
how much they're about this
connectedness well one of the things
that's perfect because one of the things
I'm folk I've been interested in for a
long time as the kinesthetics the
embodied nature of all the so when you
say participatory knowing of course the
obvious point is that there is no
non-participatory knowing I think the
propositional depends on the procedural
for sort of a constraining reasons okay
I think the procedural depends on the
perspective of for things to come out of
like Marlowe Ponte and then I think for
sort of high daguerreian reasons and the
deeper aspects of it consign the
perspective all ultimately depends on
the participatory
okay okay here's the address to that
what are the things that interests me in
the in the history up now and then and
the stuff that I've written and my
exemplar of this is Yvonne village just
for historical reasons and I know I know
there's millions of people now who were
working on these sorts of things but I'm
not on finite so I'm not familiar with
their work but Ilic pointed out a long
time ago that for instance in the
medieval the world people saw and
experienced and smelled and you know the
whole history of sensation business and
and so so one of the things that
interests me is ways of getting a
getting a an experiential access to the
fluidity of sensation what's one of the
things poetry and art is about oh I
agree that's why I follow Corbin up in
this series by plucking both far-field
yeah that's great so one of the points I
was gonna make about how this is
relevant to the whole issue about the
meeting crisis is and then I also want
to bring up something a connection to it
it's that you I think you do talk about
in one of your books but first of the
connection to the meaning crisis is I
think that that all that sub
propositional stuff is where most of the
connectedness of meaning is being made
and I think that psychology and the
cognitive science is supporting that and
as our culture has become in Braille or
I see tyranny we've long yeah I mean
obviously we still implicitly depend as
you've said on all those other kinds of
knowing for a cognitive agency but we
culturally cannot validate it or
celebrate it or access it or educate it
in any sort of system
way and I think that's a significant
contributory because because we try to
do it from the top down yeah yeah
alright yeah ok super you you know do
you must know David Abrams first book
the spell of the sensuous no I don't
read it like right now because because
he can text all this and I've been
jealous of him for a million years
because he makes an argument that sounds
a little peculiar on the face of it but
it's very persuasive that this all
started with alphabet the technology of
the alphabet okay okay well be Abram
Abram was the first time I heard about
that because he's the one that
introduced me to long and Perry and and
an image makes this argument too he does
it very neatly in a couple of places one
in the book of human saint-victor the
text so Abram and Abram makes a pretty
interesting and I think persuasive
argument that the the alphabetic
technology in particular not not just
writing but the alphabet was was
profoundly disruptive and drove us all
into our heads you know done extensive
work on the effects of literacy on
cognition and I'm gonna be also talking
soon yeah people keep people keep trying
to get me to read my Gilchrist's books
and I just haven't done it yet but yeah
I gather he says the same kind of stuff
so that's great what's what's valuable
to me as a scientist is the fact that a
lot of people independently are
converging on this kind of argument and
this kind of analysis and I pay
attention to that I mean I science
ultimately depends on judgments of
plausibility because we we have to we
can't consider everything you can't
infer
finally being seduced at Tom and so
before during and after our scientific
experimentation were dependent on our
plausibility judgments one of the one of
the things that makes things more
plausible to us as when you get a lot of
independent convergence so I find that
the fact that so many people are
converging around these points in point
for me it suggests what what Tillich
calls a compass that we're getting we're
getting to a potential you know you know
an event of timing
not just of time where the course of
things good eventually be altered no
it's really interesting to hear that's
great because that confirms you know as
I haven't been in academia for 25 years
or so and so so what I do is I go about
my own way and do my own things and then
every every decade or so I drop back in
and look around to see what people are
doing and I've had that sense that oh
yeah well they're doing the same thing
over here and over here and isn't that
nice because I think I said that a long
time ago and and what's interesting I
mean I'm I'm kind of stunned at Korriban
and at the relevance of some of the
things that are really central to his
vision that are they're really pertinent
here I mean sometimes you have to kind
of split to read him in the way that I
want to read him but there's so much
that's right about the way that he was
trying to lead us and and that idea so
that's interesting that's great oh I
guess what I'm bringing to the table
appears to get you to see and you're
dropping back in perhaps you're dropping
back in right now that things that you
might not have expected to be converging
with Coburn's Worth are now converging
with it like what's called for
science which I'm an example there's a
part of what I do and I just gave you
some examples of you know the
connections between sort of you know
very tough nuts and bolts analytic
philosophy cognitive science and this
kind of stuff and it's not a flimsy
vague kind of connection yeah yeah I try
to argue it explicitly that it is okay
alright so I have to pay attention to
your stuff Rodi damn it's just yeah
because there are so many connections
you know life is finite and I'm getting
old I mean got me back when I was 30 and
40 years old and it was teaching eight
courses a year it was pretty easy to
sort of you know make connections right
left and now it's just harder because
I'm really interested I mean I'm
seriously interested in some of the
cognitive science work that I'm that
I've badly got you know connected to
recently because it's so it's so
obviously pertinent but and then the
other thing which you immediately
recognize is personally transformative I
just recently discovered Qi Gong and
bodywork um
which you know it's just all how could I
mean and it's obvious about it yeah you
cuz the thing you would say is how could
I have been so stupid
well exactly I was so stupid
I've been telling myself and writing
about the necessity of you know
connections with the physical world
everything and in the last several
months or whatever it's been
I've actually been enacting it because I
did meditation for years and years you
have to do a moment and as soon as you
do I mean the first thing I realized was
all right if you breathe all this
actually transformative I was lucky
because when I when I took up the
practice is way back in 91 so that's
what about 29 years ago I was lucky the
people that taught me taught me a
meditative practice for parce not a
contemplative practice Mehta and Tai Chi
Chuan as an ecology and so that has been
a lesson I very very deeply learned that
you need all three of those well let me
just put a footnote on that I mean I've
been a carpenter and a gardener and I
can build buildings and I can swing a
hammer and I can do things with stone
but that was always true distinct you
know I could do I could do my
intellectual work and then I could go
out and build a building and they were
too far apart and I and so I would
always tell myself oh you're really
connected to the earth you know I really
yeah you know I'm not just an academic
which was true but I didn't have the
middle ground in this series I talked
about the dour stuff and playing Tai Chi
because you play it you don't do it mmm
perfect URI I talked about serious play
yeah I give touch each one as an example
of enacted imaginal as soon as I started
doing it and that's a long story but
that was I thought oh well this is this
is enacted around
no because I've always I had dream sense
Oh since the 70s I had known you know
job you really ought to dance more
because I had a girl the girlfriend who
was a dancer and I never did it and and
there's still all sorts of psychic
reasons why not this is a and without
something with just an analogue of dance
you know I don't break its so it's
perfect it's interesting because I had
one of those aha you know that is just
an intellectual insight but it's an
existential insight and when you talk
about those they often seem trivial yeah
yeah the impact on me because I've been
doing so I was already in grad school
and everything and I was having success
and in what you could call like the
intellectual domain right and then it
for reasons that have to do again with
my idiosyncratic autobiography I'd taken
up these practices especially the Tai
Chi and and I was practicing very
religiously
and yeah you know and other and I notice
that I was picking up skills and I was
thinking of sort of self-defense yeah
yeah but my friends started coming to me
and they started saying what's happening
and I said what do you mean and they
said you're arguing differently you're
writing and I went oh and that's where I
got my first deep inkling of that level
below the propositional and that's the
level where the deep transformation and
where the deep meaning making and here's
another here's another example at least
I think of the disjunction that I that I
was experiencing that is now getting
smaller so so I had a kind of break a
few years ago and then I wrote some I
wrote a book of poems that got published
and that's and then that's wonderful and
I loved it and then they stopped coming
and then I was back again to you know
what do I do and because of when I was
writing the poems I thought this is it I
mean this is what I should be doing but
then they
you know it just became it became a rote
performance and I had and I didn't have
a middle ground do you know yeah and and
because and it's a little too simplistic
but not maybe not I didn't have a
movement practice to connect the two
sides that's all and that I mean there's
there's deep aspects of about that again
and you can connect it to that cognitive
science because cerebellum right we used
to think it was just about political
balance but we're discovering the
cerebellum as connections to the frontal
cortex and what it's doing is it's it's
like the cerebellar cortex loop has a
lot to do with your capacity to bridge
so you yeah the cerebellum doesn't just
care about sort of contingencies right
in the world that cares about
contingencies within your brain and so
like if you don't get that cerebellum
cortex loop running really well just
never yeah yeah that's fantastic that's
just fantastic yeah I I did I've done a
couple of little lectures stealing from
the entropic brain hypothesis and yeah
yeah I took yeah so the autobiographical
thing is that I happened across Michael
Pollan's book which I think it was true
of a lot of people and it brought me
right back to 1990 when when there when
I was just about to either do oil and
macho Rama and there there serve craze I
you know they're they're cognitive
science stuff and that was when I
discovered Hillman and Korriban so I did
sir
so I had this really difficult decision
to make whether to do the sort of crazy
ID garyun natural
you know much your honor and for reality
cognitive science stuff which was just
fascinating to me or to go over and do
Helmand in Corbin so 25 years later POW
and publishes his book and I'm right
back reading the embodied mind which I
had which I actually sold in 1992 just
to get it out of my office friends and
colleagues with Evan Thompson great and
so here's an interesting synchronicity
Evan was supposed to teach the course at
the University of Toronto called
Buddhism and cognitive science he
couldn't teach it and then he
recommended me and that's where I
developed the original argument that
became my video series a week that's
really great promotional but I if you
want it's not I was gonna say quick and
easy but it's like there's 50 videos and
they're an hour long but you know
somewhat fast access to those
connections yeah somewhat fast is not 50
hours well I think I think Jared had
said number 47 and 48 or something again
references to early episode again I
don't want to points you want to go back
and say well what can I get back to the
1990 and reconnect to that oh yeah
what's do stream there's parts in the
series where I'm actually trying to
where I actually do that argue for how
to do that okay okay yeah cuz I do want
to I do want to see that have you got
anything you've got any manuscripts or
anything written about this stuff well I
do and I have bit some places
right now turning the whole of the
series into a book okay okay we'll be
done okay
this year sweet all right and there's
another book coming out that I'm doing
with Daniel Greg called the cognitive
continuum from insight to enlightenment
that tries to at least track out all the
cognitive science from inside
experiences oh wow
trying to give it unified and integrated
explanation for that and why they have
such an impact on people's sense of
meaning and how that relates to because
we've kept these things all separate but
how that relates rationality insight and
wisdom together we'll see whether it's
that's that's I will I will I will I
will flag your stuff for my current
students I got about 12 of them and
we're doing a little online course on
court bands influence on on poets in the
United States so we're making the
transition from core bands idea of talk
wheel to the uses made by Native it and
other bits of his cosmology by Robert by
Charles Olson and Robert Duncan and then
there's a whole flood of of poets who
were either explicitly or or well the
who are explicitly influenced by Corbin
so so the issues for us at the moment at
least in that class are entirely
embodied because of Charles Olsen's
emphasis on projective verse and the
breath and his idea of proprioceptive
cognition which is just what the sort of
thing that we're talking about here and
so I'm trying to I'm trying to ground my
students in you know immediately
and the other the other thing that
that's crucial for me is that yeah I was
a teacher of biology I'm an invertebrate
zoologist and the reason and the reason
for that is that I looked at an insect
once at the age at the age of 30 when I
thought I was going to be a physicist I
discovered the Chris Amell and insects
and and it just you know you'd sound
silly at the time like you were saying
but that was a transformative moment sin
and so one of the one of the reasons to
do poetry and to and to do art and dance
and movement is quite simply to animate
the world I mean not it's not that it's
coming from you it's the it's part of
the dialogue and I thought yes is
interesting you're talking in terms of
meaning and and because you know that
and I'm thinking about that while you
were talking that whole time I don't
care about meaning because it's me in
the sense that it's not it's never been
it's like I said to the young'uns once
that I didn't care about God and they
they didn't like that at all because I
you know I don't care about God at all
because I'm much more I mean he's not
interesting I mean the angels are
interesting but God is totally
uninteresting and so's meaning I mean
who gives a about meaning I want to
look at insects and plants and and and
other people and the meaning is sort of
that'sthat's like you said that's it I
forget how you what your terminology is
but that's that's a that's a
propositional issue and I don't give a
damn about propositional issues I want
to get the balls of reality you know no
no no no no because
because that's the other thing that yeah
that that's the other thing that I'm
really curious about and and you would
know something about this is that ideas
that look abstract actually change your
perceptions they can say when I'm using
the word meaning as I said I'm using
IIIi put it as a metaphor for we're
using something about language that is
in some way analogous to the sense of
connectedness which we're talking about
when you want to give so I'm pointing to
that no no I understand yeah so the guy
I wanted to talk about is Michael
Anderson and he's got a book called
after phrenology and a bunch of papers
on what he calls the massive
redeployment hypothesis is I'll give you
didn't give me a second on this and the
idea is we used to think you know this
function is located here in the brain
and Borla and that's what he calls it
after phrenology we're now getting the
same area the brain gets actually used
you know biologists you know something
about like exaptation right about how
one function can be done so the idea is
the brain does something deeply
analogous to that it's written trolling
right handedness and can use that for
manipulating sound in speech right and
and so I I think in a lot of ways what
you can see is you can see stuff being
exacted upwards out of the participatory
and then and and we can get and that but
there's also feedback back down right
it's it's sort of a bottom-up and
top-down thing at the same time actually
John Kenney and I published work on this
a long time ago in the nineties we were
talking about Lake often Johnston's work
or now yeah buddy
metaphor yeah we we didn't we weren't
arguing against the phenomena of pervade
the pervasiveness of of metaphor but we
thought that their model was a little
too simplistic to borrow not enough
I think Michael Anderson's work point so
yes stuff does come up okay yeah I'd
like to take a look at that because
because people you know ever since I was
I don't know pretty pretty young people
would say but this isn't interesting
what you're talking about it's all just
abstract and then then I would always
excuse me no no it's not abstract it
changes your life there's two ways in
which people are dismissive when they do
that right but it's not paying attention
I mean this name might not be important
to you but within cognitive psychology
the work on reasoning and rationality
there's a there's Kahneman and Tversky
they're the ones that came up with this
idea of sort of a swan process okay
Barbara Tversky has a new book out
called mind the emotion mm-hmm how a lot
of our abstract normal logic abilities I
would say are exhausted out of our
spatial navigation by increasing
empirical experimental yeah yeah I keep
I keep this I keep rolling it into that
and I have two hard things for the
students and saying by the way now the
scientists are actually giving this data
to produce things people which is saying
before yeah that's pretty yeah nearly
has been exacted out of physical balance
yeah it's concerning to justice like in
all kinds of more abstract things but
that's why but I think for example a
clear example of the imaginal is our
relationship to justice we can only you
have to we have to activate all of that
balanced machinery through the through
these image the imaginal symbols in
order to talk about right there's an
artifact ideal of justice I think as
Coromant says without that intermediary
mm we co activate what we need the
balanced machinery and get it they're
talking to that you know the
abstract ideal language of justice there
that you can't you can't do without that
Center yeah yeah all right there you're
bad of course yeah
what that there's a phrase that he uses
that I love he says it once but he says
Aristotle's abstract categories are
nothing but the dead bodies of angels
[Laughter]
yeah yeah it is
oh there's there's too many things we
should get together sometime in the
flesh I should yeah that would be yeah
it'd be nice to you know I have another
conversation to at some point because I
think I mean you've had a deep influence
on my work yeah but I think that there's
a lot of connections but I think yes and
now I'm screwed because I'm gonna have
to watch a whole bunch of those videos
and Joe could you send could you resend
me the links to those yeah yeah I just
make sure I make sure I have them
I'm the other the other thing is I'm
just going to get overloaded with
exciting things that's fine I mean it
comes and it comes and goes I go through
pigs where I where I gather things and
then goods where I throw out the ones
it's just that I'm not sure what my
criteria for discard are right now well
I just I just had my 68th birthday and
so you know and so finitude is
approaching and so I'm trying to figure
out I mean yeah from the top down I'm
not trying to figure out from the top
down
trying to figure out where the energy
wants to be you know for the stuff that
I'm most interested in doing next and
and it almost it has to do it has to it
has to relate to teaching and it has to
relate to you know a reanimation of the
world for people at this at this primary
level so I'm thinking poetry and theater
and dance and bodywork but I love I love
to be a bending I'm a scientist by
training so I love to be able to bring
in the neuroscience you know because
because that's tremendously because that
allows like I'm going down to Brunswick
Maine and one of the to do a thing for
the Brunswick unions on Saturday and one
of the primary guys there is an engineer
and so you always have you always have
the engineer in the audience who sitting
there and and is incredibly schizoid
about his day job which is engineering
and then he's had his union break down
and he's got all these imagination
things in there and he don't know how to
deal with it and if you can show a
picture of the cerebellum flyering
then you can suck them into so this is
really good I'm in conversation with a
lot of people for example I'm in
conversation with Rafe Kelly and he's
putting together like he's been put in a
community of practices so what he does
is he he's created in ecology practices
I'm some videos out there mhmmm where
he's basically teaching people how to do
parkour in nature mmm sort of martial
art stuff so mindfulness practice and
also sitting around a campfire and
circling doing a circling practice and
integrating me all together and he's
been and he and I have been talking
because he's he's using some of the
ideas from cognitive science that I've
been presenting and he's using that to
try and sharpen and develop and refine
this ecology of practices and the
community
it's supporting and so that kind of
dialogue is it's not just what I'm
saying Tom it's not just abstract theory
that's precisely what I'm interested in
doing and I and I'm not I don't have
them I don't have the psyche or the
resources to do it out of myself
I gotta participate with people who have
different backgrounds because I write my
default mode is to think and the things
I can do but I don't do them naturally
in groups because I'm dude I'm too
defensive you know and and so I I
recognized that and I'm so so boy can
you point me to something that I could
read about what he and or you ordering
as rape has written anything he's done a
couple of videos where he and I are
talking about these connections I think
there's three or four in total I don't
know if Jared's familiar with them but
they're out there they're on my channel
okay man alright I don't find him you
see that in practice what's interesting
and there's also videos I think that
I've a link to where he's actually in
the literally in the field in a field
students about how to take these ideas
right and how they how they are mediated
into and then how they are enriched by
these embodied practices and the
engagement and it's all about I once
said to him I said what you're doing all
these practices and maybe this aligns
with what you're saying Tom if you're
trying to get people to fall in love
with yeah yeah yeah I mean I used to do
that in the context of biology courses
you know you go out and you collect
insects you look at the flowers you
learn the trees you learn the stars you
know I mean but we call that science
when and when in fact that's not really
what was going on yeah you know it's
falling in love with the world that's
precisely and and and I want to find
ways that don't look like bio I mean I
yeah that's a good way of putting it
because I I do I could do I can do that
you know I'm you know I have a handful
of students who became entomologists
because I dragged them out with another
you know that's it it's it's it's like
poetry is humanities lab and yeah you
know I was just talking to a guy the
other day said oh that's a poetry is
it's humanities lab but he tees a decent
English teacher and and and and yeah so
that's yeah that is perfect that really
that's what I that's what I'm interested
in doing both your work is just how much
it integrates and connects like all
these different domains I mean both of
you having scientific backgrounds but
also these deeply philosophical and
spiritual backgrounds and you're able to
draw and combine all these different
things it's so it's so nice to see that
there's people who are transdisciplinary
because yeah yeah it is really sweet I
don't have too much more time right now
but I would love to either do this again
or whatever you want to do John yeah I
think there's definite residence between
us so I think there's a lot we can
explore together like you know maybe
okay yeah let's let's do that and okay
okay sweet oh that's that's great I
appreciate that not look at your stuff
too and let me just say I don't know
what state it's in now but in 2021
there's going to be a record by a
conference at McGill in in cotton in it
is co-sponsored by the Harvard Divinity
School and Charles Stein oh yeah I mean
he's he's one of them he's he's the guy
that he
and a colleague estate he's actually a
student at McGill a hottie fuckery he
and Charlie Stang are doing going to put
together this massive core band
conference so get in touch with Stang
okay well I talked about Stan's work at
eugene emailing and tell him that I sent
you
yeah because that would be a place where
we could get together and chat if you
could come too if you can make it to
Montreal so can I just about what it is
for me that's not bad yeah sometimes
sometime in 2021 but I don't know one
yet yes definitely for that okay Jared
yeah you can stay keep us yeah in
communication and I will upset and I'm
gonna spread the word about your stuff
John frum to my students to who I know
will be interested yeah okay sweet
that's fantastic this is fun this is
great
I'm serious playing delight it yes it is
some serious player and it really that
yeah
thank you for connecting things I would
we've recorded this I would load it to
youtube somewhere
sure yeah if you do let me know I could
yeah that would be great so who's
hosting this got the recording here I
could you send me the file directly I'll
upload it on to my channel ok sweet yeah
yeah that's that's fantastic
and you know and you're both sort of
committing to doing well I want to I'm
committing I'll definitely talk with you
again prom yeah much like that yeah so
lets you know if people know that
something looked forward to that's also
good and I'll definitely definitely
email
Charles Stang and start getting my
antenna out for these conferences yeah
yeah because that'd be great that would
be terrific
okay well we'll talk again soon after
I've looked at some of your stuff and I
and I but but might might my inclination
is to say I'm really interested in in
the practical application that yeah the
video series that take a look at some of
the conversations I have with Rafe
Kelley where that connection is really
being made how does he spell the first
name are AF e and Kelley ke lle why and
like I said you just go to my YouTube
channel you'll find that there okay John
bacon conversation other people comment
there and you can find all those videos
there sweet great okay thank you both
thank you very much okay okay okay great
yeah no it's fantastic thanks hey so
thanks so much for putting this up yeah
your your sense that was there the
connection between us was very prescient
very clear yeah I think we I think we're
gonna have a lot of good conversations
and I think they would be valuable to
other people so yeah just send me the
file um once you're ready and then I'll
upload it onto my channel and there we
go
sure yeah sure you know well and I'll
tweet about it a post and LinkedIn post
on Facebook so we'll get you know to
10,000 people or so
sort of a national interest in it and
hopefully that'll get it going I mean
the fact that I've talked about Tom's
work so much both in my courses and on
in a lot of my videos it's it's really
nice that a lot of people will be able
to see him in person my gosh he's a
charming guy yeah charismatic leader
arming it's just sort of a blow I was
really really impressive what a sweet
guy
my gosh yeah though I've really enjoyed
tuning into his podcast for the past
year so it's always such a pleasure so
yeah it was great the dynamic that just
sort of a Rhodes like so fun so again a
very big thanks to you on there thank
you know you know and having you there I
think there's a moderator in the future
is probably good idea at least for Beth
you know sure you you it was your sense
of the connections that help to you know
to to ferment the the discussion so I
thought that's very useful yeah
wonderful yeah I had some others sort of
specific ideas in mind for where the
conversation could go that I could bring
up but it just went there already stuff
yeah I'm glad where are you Jared where
are you yeah I'm in Madison Wisconsin
right now right right okay delightful
delightful town not so many options here
for me for graduate studies right now
and so somewhere down the line probably
but in the meantime I can get involved
with a lot of cool independent stuff
like you cannot get to narrowed into
specialization as long as you can yeah
okay well I should go too then so thank
you very much for that was a lot of fun
and it's always great to meet people
that you read on each writers yeah and
it's it's encouraging to me because it
sounds like my interpretation of Tom's
work is one that he's very resonant with
definitely that's always encouraging
okay so like I said send me an email
you know I don't know how you'll send me
the file are you gonna Dropbox it or
what yeah probably Google Drive if that
were extremely it'll Drive Google Drive
it sent me an email with the link to the
Google Drive and then and then I'll
upload it and then Oh like I said I'll
promote it they'll send you an email
back letting you know that all about
skirt mm-hmm I'd be happy to do a little
graphic design for the thumbnail if that
would be useful
please Abby that's well within my
wheelhouse
okay well then please do that that would
be excellent all right wonderful and
sometime in the future I'd really love
to talk to you about nishitani
yes yes when I would so the next series
is after Socrates but the series after
that is uh the god beyond God and
nishitani is gonna figure it very
largely in the nothing this is one of
the absolute great books alright really
it's it's it's one of the top five books
I've read in my life yeah yeah I
remember you mentioned that in in no
electricity reason yeah I just got this
group of friends together and all of the
people who were able to stay on with the
book work super impacted read it's not
in the abyss yeah it was so beneficial
to do it in community yeah yeah I read
it
usually on my own and then I read it
with somebody else so in that second
reading with somebody else was extremely
valuable yeah yeah now we're looking at
trying to put together a sort of reading
I drawing on like expertise so that's
that's in the works for me right now
just starting out with that without that
would be really cool to be out there and
available for people who wanna prefer
stack already because I'd be interested
in promoting sure yeah definitely so
okay Jarek
yeah but wonderful immediately thank you
again
wonderful meeting you thank you again
for all of this will be a touch again
and Shawn's good very much
you